<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Steve&#39;s Blog</title>
        <link>https://stvpj.com/</link>
        <description>Recent content on Steve&#39;s Blog</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <copyright>Steve</copyright>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 20 Apr 2025 09:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://stvpj.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>Agile Isn’t What You Think</title>
        <link>https://stvpj.com/p/agile-pitfalls-measuring-value/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Apr 2025 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://stvpj.com/p/agile-pitfalls-measuring-value/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="https://stvpj.com/p/agile-pitfalls-measuring-value/header.png" alt="Featured image of post Agile Isn’t What You Think" /&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-pitfalls-of-one-size-fits-all-agile-why-most-agile-implementations-miss-the-point&#34;&gt;The Pitfalls of One-Size-Fits-All Agile: Why Most Agile Implementations Miss the Point
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Agile is everywhere. Or so it seems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Walk into nearly any modern software organization and you’ll be told they “do agile.” There are stand-ups. Sprints. Story points. Jira boards. Retros. There&amp;rsquo;s probably a release train or two. On paper, it looks like agility. But in reality, it&amp;rsquo;s anything but.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite widespread adoption of agile methodologies and frameworks, most companies still fail to embody what agile truly stands for. What we’re seeing isn’t agile—it’s agile theater. A performance of rituals devoid of the mindset and principles that actually make agile work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why? Because no one wants to talk about the real reason agile fails in big organizations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;True agility means you won’t know exactly how long something will take, or how much it will cost, before you begin.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s the uncomfortable truth. And it&amp;rsquo;s the one truth that almost no one in a boardroom wants to hear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-illusion-of-predictability&#34;&gt;The Illusion of Predictability
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let’s be clear: &lt;strong&gt;agile is not a framework. It’s a mindset.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the Agile Manifesto was written, it was a response to the rigidity of traditional software development—a world in which long-term plans rarely survived contact with reality. Agile promised something better: flexibility, collaboration, and continuous delivery of value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But large organizations have tried to retrofit agile into the very structures it was meant to replace. They’ve imposed predictability on top of adaptability. They&amp;rsquo;ve institutionalized delivery cadences and backlogs and roadmaps and burndown charts in an effort to make agile feel safe and familiar. In doing so, they&amp;rsquo;ve fundamentally undermined it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frameworks like SAFe and LeSS may offer a sense of control at scale, but they often do so by compromising on the core agile principle: &lt;strong&gt;embrace uncertainty&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because at the heart of true agility is a simple reality: &lt;em&gt;you are building something new, and you cannot plan certainty into discovery.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-agile-needs-uncertainty&#34;&gt;Why Agile Needs Uncertainty
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Agile Manifesto begins with individuals and interactions over processes and tools. It emphasizes working software over comprehensive documentation. It encourages customer collaboration over contract negotiation. And above all, it values responding to change over following a plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are not project management practices. These are philosophical commitments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you take them seriously, then it follows that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You &lt;strong&gt;cannot guarantee fixed scopes, timelines, or budgets&lt;/strong&gt; up front.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You &lt;strong&gt;will learn things mid-flight&lt;/strong&gt; that will force you to change direction.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You &lt;strong&gt;must give teams the autonomy&lt;/strong&gt; to solve problems in ways that aren&amp;rsquo;t fully spec’d before they begin.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is what makes agile work—and what makes it so uncomfortable for command-and-control management styles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;velocity-is-not-value&#34;&gt;Velocity Is Not Value
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the absence of real agility, organizations default to what they can measure. And the easiest thing to measure is &lt;strong&gt;velocity&lt;/strong&gt;—how many story points a team completes per sprint. But velocity is a local optimization. It tells you how &lt;em&gt;busy&lt;/em&gt; your team is, not how &lt;em&gt;effective&lt;/em&gt; they are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Velocity is about output. Agile is about outcomes.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can double your team’s velocity and still build something no one wants. You can hit every sprint goal and still miss the market. You can have high throughput and zero impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where most agile transformations break down: they prioritize activity over value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;so-what-should-we-measure&#34;&gt;So, What Should We Measure?
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;If agile is about delivering value, then &lt;strong&gt;value&lt;/strong&gt; must be what we measure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But value isn’t a simple thing. It’s not a number you pull out of Jira. It’s not a burndown chart or a feature count.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Value is what helps your organization succeed.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It shows up in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increased revenue&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reduced customer churn&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improved user satisfaction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Greater market share&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stronger engagement or retention&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are &lt;strong&gt;lagging indicators&lt;/strong&gt; of success—they tell you after the fact whether what you built actually made a difference. But because they lag, they’re not always useful for day-to-day decision-making.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s where &lt;strong&gt;proxy metrics&lt;/strong&gt; come in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;proxy-metrics-aligning-toward-impact&#34;&gt;Proxy Metrics: Aligning Toward Impact
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;To make agile actionable in the short term, teams need &lt;strong&gt;leading indicators&lt;/strong&gt; that signal whether they’re moving in the right direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Engineering&lt;/strong&gt; teams focus on delivery health:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cycle time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deployment frequency&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lead time for changes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change failure rate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These help identify bottlenecks, inefficiencies, and delivery risks. They don’t measure value directly—but they indicate how reliably the team can deliver value when it’s found.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Product&lt;/strong&gt; teams focus on signals of product-market fit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Activation rates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feature adoption&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Retention curves&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Customer satisfaction scores&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Net Promoter Scores (NPS)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Task success rates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These help gauge whether users are finding what’s being built useful and valuable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real power comes from aligning these two sets of indicators: ensuring that &lt;strong&gt;delivery teams are enabled to move fast and safely&lt;/strong&gt;, while &lt;strong&gt;product teams are focused on the highest-leverage problems.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;efficiency-vs-effectiveness-know-the-difference&#34;&gt;Efficiency vs. Effectiveness: Know the Difference
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here’s the critical distinction that many agile teams blur:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Delivery teams&lt;/strong&gt; should be optimized for &lt;strong&gt;efficiency&lt;/strong&gt;—to execute with speed, quality, and stability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Product teams&lt;/strong&gt; should be optimized for &lt;strong&gt;effectiveness&lt;/strong&gt;—to ensure that what gets delivered actually matters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you optimize only for speed, you risk building the wrong thing faster.&lt;br&gt;
If you optimize only for insight, you risk discovering great opportunities too slowly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Agile is about continuously improving both sides of that equation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That means:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creating a &lt;strong&gt;clear separation of concerns&lt;/strong&gt; between prioritization and execution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Funding and structuring teams around &lt;strong&gt;outcomes, not projects&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Giving product and delivery teams &lt;strong&gt;joint ownership of goals&lt;/strong&gt;, but distinct accountability for &lt;strong&gt;what&lt;/strong&gt; gets done and &lt;strong&gt;how&lt;/strong&gt; it gets done.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;agility-without-illusions&#34;&gt;Agility Without Illusions
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The real tragedy of faux-agile is that it gives organizations the illusion of adaptability without requiring any of the discipline or humility that true agility demands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Agile is not about adopting a framework. It’s about cultivating a mindset:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One that values &lt;strong&gt;learning over knowing&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One that embraces &lt;strong&gt;change over control&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One that prioritizes &lt;strong&gt;customer outcomes over internal process fidelity&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you strip away the jargon, the tickets, and the tooling, this is the real work:&lt;br&gt;
→ &lt;strong&gt;Helping organizations get comfortable with uncertainty.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
→ &lt;strong&gt;Focusing teams on value, not velocity.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
→ &lt;strong&gt;And measuring success not by how much you deliver—but by how much it matters.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;final-thought&#34;&gt;Final Thought
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;If your agile process gives you the illusion of predictability but none of the adaptability, it’s not agile. It’s a façade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if your stakeholders expect certainty in timelines and cost before any real discovery has happened, they’re not signing up for agile—they’re asking for waterfall with daily standups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question isn’t “are we agile?”&lt;br&gt;
The real question is: &lt;strong&gt;do we have the courage to let go of control in pursuit of value?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Why Product Managers Should Trust Their Gut When Data Falls Short</title>
        <link>https://stvpj.com/p/why-product-managers-should-trust-their-gut-when-data-falls-short/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Apr 2025 09:08:36 +0100</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://stvpj.com/p/why-product-managers-should-trust-their-gut-when-data-falls-short/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="https://stvpj.com/p/why-product-managers-should-trust-their-gut-when-data-falls-short/header.png" alt="Featured image of post Why Product Managers Should Trust Their Gut When Data Falls Short" /&gt;&lt;h1 id=&#34;why-product-managers-should-trust-their-gut-when-data-falls-short&#34;&gt;Why Product Managers Should Trust Their Gut When Data Falls Short
&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;As Product Managers, we’re often told to “let the data speak” and to rely on hard evidence to validate our hypotheses. And rightly so—data is a powerful tool for minimizing risk and understanding user behavior. However, there’s a vital piece of the product innovation puzzle that is often overlooked: intuition. When the right data isn’t available or doesn’t exist, your gut can be your most valuable ally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, some of the most transformative innovations we celebrate today were born in moments when data was either nonexistent or irrelevant. Let’s explore why Product Managers shouldn’t shy away from trusting their instincts when navigating uncharted waters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;data-is-a-compass-not-a-crystal-ball&#34;&gt;Data Is a Compass, Not a Crystal Ball
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Marty Cagan, author of &lt;em&gt;Inspired&lt;/em&gt;, emphasizes the limitations of relying solely on data. He writes, &lt;em&gt;“Data is essential, but it only tells you about the past. If you want to invent the future, you have to look beyond the data.”&lt;/em&gt; Data can show us what has worked before, but it rarely points to what will work in the future, especially when you’re venturing into unexplored territory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a Product Manager tries to innovate in a space that’s new or undefined, historical data often falls short. Imagine being the first to propose something like the iPhone. What data would have validated that hypothesis? None. Yet, Steve Jobs famously said, &lt;em&gt;“People don’t know what they want until you show it to them.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;visionary-thinking-often-precedes-data&#34;&gt;Visionary Thinking Often Precedes Data
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some of the most game-changing innovations weren’t built on data—they were built on a deep understanding of human needs and the courage to make bold decisions. Steve Jobs’ intuition about user experience led to products that redefined industries. Had Apple waited for market research to prove demand, the iPhone might never have happened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, Pawel Huryn, product leader and author, argues that &lt;em&gt;“great product managers are great storytellers—they imagine a better world and then find a way to make it real.”&lt;/em&gt; In the early stages of product development, storytelling and vision often fill the gaps where data cannot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;when-to-trust-your-gut&#34;&gt;When to Trust Your Gut
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trusting your gut doesn’t mean ignoring data—it means knowing when it isn’t enough. Here are some scenarios where intuition can be invaluable:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When entering uncharted markets:&lt;/strong&gt; No historical data exists for truly innovative ideas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When experimenting with new paradigms:&lt;/strong&gt; Early-stage products often lack the metrics to guide decisions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When responding to qualitative insights:&lt;/strong&gt; User interviews and anecdotal evidence sometimes reveal truths that numbers can’t.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pawel Huryn puts it succinctly: &lt;em&gt;“Your gut feeling is your subconscious mind processing years of experience, knowledge, and observations. It’s not irrational; it’s informed.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;balancing-data-and-intuition&#34;&gt;Balancing Data and Intuition
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The key is to strike a balance. Use data when it’s available and relevant, but don’t let the absence of perfect data paralyze you. Great Product Managers are not just analysts—they’re visionaries who can navigate ambiguity and take calculated risks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Marty Cagan reminds us, &lt;em&gt;“At the end of the day, your job is to solve problems in a way that creates value for your customers and your company. Don’t let data become an excuse for inaction.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>How Security and Data Governance Improve User Experience</title>
        <link>https://stvpj.com/p/how-security-and-data-governance-improve-user-experience/</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 19 Apr 2025 14:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://stvpj.com/p/how-security-and-data-governance-improve-user-experience/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="https://stvpj.com/p/how-security-and-data-governance-improve-user-experience/header.png" alt="Featured image of post How Security and Data Governance Improve User Experience" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enhancing User Experience through Security and Data Governance: A Product Manager&amp;rsquo;s Perspective&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We live in an age where our personal information is increasingly digitised. Every click, every search, and every online purchase leaves behind a digital footprint. As a Product Manager, my main goal is not just to deliver feature-rich applications but to ensure that these applications are safe, trustworthy, and provide an excellent user experience. One might assume that optimising for security and data governance might hinder the user experience. Contrary to that belief, I&amp;rsquo;m here to argue that enhancing security and data governance is, in fact, a significant booster to the overall user experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Building Trust&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
The most apparent benefit of security optimisation is trust. When users realise that a product or service prioritises their security, they are more likely to trust it. Trust, in the digital realm, is not just a nice-to-have; it&amp;rsquo;s a necessity. A product that loses its users&amp;rsquo; trust might as well lose its users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Smooth Experience with Fewer Interruptions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Imagine a scenario where an application gets compromised. This would lead to downtimes, emergency maintenance, or even data breaches. Each of these outcomes disrupts the user experience. By investing in security from the get-go, we ensure a seamless experience for our users, free from unexpected disruptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Empowerment through Transparency&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Data governance isn&amp;rsquo;t just about keeping user data safe; it&amp;rsquo;s about being transparent about how this data is used. By giving users a clear insight into what data is collected, why it&amp;rsquo;s collected, and how it&amp;rsquo;s used, we empower them. An empowered user is an engaged user, and an engaged user is the key to enhanced user experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tailored User Experiences without the Creepiness&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
One of the main reasons companies collect data is to provide a more tailored experience to their users. However, there&amp;rsquo;s a fine line between personalisation and intrusiveness. Proper data governance ensures that personalisation is done right, without crossing the boundaries of user comfort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compliance Equals Access&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
In today&amp;rsquo;s global market, regulatory compliance is not optional. Regulations like GDPR in Europe or CCPA in California have strict requirements regarding data privacy and security. By adhering to these regulations, we not only avoid hefty fines but ensure that our product is accessible to a broader audience without regional restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Future-proofing the Business&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Security threats and data misuse are not static; they evolve. By building a foundation based on robust security and data governance, we are preparing our product for the challenges of the future. This ensures that our users continue to have a consistent and safe experience even as digital landscapes change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;User Feedback and Continuous Improvement&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
When users feel safe and trust a platform, they are more likely to provide genuine feedback. This feedback is invaluable. It allows us to continuously refine and improve, ensuring the user experience keeps getting better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, security and data governance are not mere checkboxes in the product development process. They are crucial pillars that hold the weight of user trust and engagement. By integrating them into the core of our products, we are not sacrificing user experience; we are elevating it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember, in the end, it&amp;rsquo;s not just about building a product; it&amp;rsquo;s about building a relationship with our users. And like any successful relationship, it must be built on trust, transparency, and mutual respect.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>What Lean Really Means</title>
        <link>https://stvpj.com/p/what-lean-really-means/</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 19 Apr 2025 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://stvpj.com/p/what-lean-really-means/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="https://stvpj.com/p/what-lean-really-means/header.png" alt="Featured image of post What Lean Really Means" /&gt;&lt;h1 id=&#34;lean-thinking-what-it-isand-what-it-isnt&#34;&gt;Lean Thinking: What It Is—and What It Isn’t
&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lean is one of the most misunderstood concepts in modern business. It’s often mistaken for a buzzword, a quick-fix method, or worse—just another cost-cutting exercise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s start by setting the record straight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lean is not:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A miracle cure for all business problems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A synonym for “doing more with less” at any cost&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A new religion, fad, or acronym&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lean is a long-term, strategic approach to improving how organizations work—one that puts customer value at the centre and treats anything that doesn’t contribute to that value (or the safety, quality, and stability of the organization) as waste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lean is a philosophy of continuous improvement that eliminates waste, empowers people, and focuses relentlessly on delivering value to customers.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-three-pillars-of-lean&#34;&gt;The Three Pillars of Lean
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;All credible definitions of Lean align around three core goals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deliver better value to customers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do more with less&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ensure quality and long-term sustainability are never compromised&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Organizations that embrace Lean behave in consistent, observable ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Everyone understands what customers truly value&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Continuous improvement is part of daily operations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Respect for people is central&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The organization aligns long-term thinking with short-term actions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lean becomes part of the culture—not just a program&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-toyota-way-14-principles-of-lean-excellence&#34;&gt;The Toyota Way: 14 Principles of Lean Excellence
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Jeffrey Liker’s &lt;em&gt;The Toyota Way&lt;/em&gt; breaks Lean into 14 principles, grouped into four themes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-philosophy-as-a-foundation&#34;&gt;1. Philosophy as a Foundation
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Make decisions based on long-term thinking&lt;/strong&gt;, not short-term gains.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-the-right-process-produces-the-right-results&#34;&gt;2. The Right Process Produces the Right Results
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Create continuous flow&lt;/strong&gt; to surface problems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Use pull systems&lt;/strong&gt; to avoid overproduction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Level out workloads&lt;/strong&gt; (heijunka)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Stop to fix problems&lt;/strong&gt; and get quality right the first time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. Standardize tasks&lt;/strong&gt; as the basis for improvement and empowerment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. Use visual controls&lt;/strong&gt; so no problems stay hidden&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8. Use only reliable, thoroughly tested technology&lt;/strong&gt; that supports people&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-add-value-by-developing-people-and-partners&#34;&gt;3. Add Value by Developing People and Partners
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9. Grow leaders&lt;/strong&gt; who understand and teach the philosophy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10. Build great teams&lt;/strong&gt; that align with company goals&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;11. Respect partners and suppliers&lt;/strong&gt;—help them improve too&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;4-continuous-problem-solving-drives-learning&#34;&gt;4. Continuous Problem Solving Drives Learning
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;12. Go see for yourself (genchi genbutsu)&lt;/strong&gt; to understand situations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;13. Make decisions slowly by consensus&lt;/strong&gt;, implement them quickly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;14. Become a learning organization&lt;/strong&gt; through reflection and improvement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-8-wastes-of-lean&#34;&gt;The 8 Wastes of Lean
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lean identifies 8 common forms of waste, present in both manufacturing and service sectors:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Waiting&lt;/strong&gt; – Delays between process steps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overproduction&lt;/strong&gt; – Doing more than needed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rework&lt;/strong&gt; – Fixing mistakes or defects&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Motion&lt;/strong&gt; – Unnecessary movement of people&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Transport&lt;/strong&gt; – Unneeded movement of materials or information&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Processing&lt;/strong&gt; – Extra work that doesn’t add value&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inventory&lt;/strong&gt; – Excess stock or queued activity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Talent&lt;/strong&gt; – Underusing people&amp;rsquo;s skills and creativity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;final-thoughts-lean-as-a-culture-not-a-checklist&#34;&gt;Final Thoughts: Lean as a Culture, Not a Checklist
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lean is not a toolset. It’s a mindset.&lt;br&gt;
It’s not a one-time transformation—it’s a way of thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It asks us to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Empower people&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Eliminate waste&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pursue purpose&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Continuously improve&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s hard work. But for organizations willing to commit, Lean offers a path to more meaningful value, healthier teams, and resilient long-term success.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Archives</title>
        <link>https://stvpj.com/archives/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 28 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://stvpj.com/archives/</guid>
        <description></description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>About Me</title>
        <link>https://stvpj.com/about-me/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://stvpj.com/about-me/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hi, I’m Steve — a builder, problem-solver, and curious technologist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog is my little home on the internet where I share experiments, reflections, and useful tools I come across. I work mostly in tech and like to explore where technology intersects with real life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for stopping by!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Links</title>
        <link>https://stvpj.com/links/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://stvpj.com/links/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Here are a few places I find value, inspiration, or connection online:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;🧠 &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.svpg.com/team/marty-cagan/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Marty Cagan — Product Influencer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;💼 &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/stvpjames/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;My LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;📰 &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://newsnotnoisejessicayellin.substack.com/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;News Not Noise — Substack by Jessica Yellin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;💻 &lt;a class=&#34;link&#34; href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/&#34;  target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;
    &gt;Hacker News&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>Search</title>
        <link>https://stvpj.com/search/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://stvpj.com/search/</guid>
        <description></description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
