<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Posts on Steve&#39;s Blog</title>
        <link>https://stvpj.com/post/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Posts on Steve&#39;s Blog</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <copyright>Steve</copyright>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 20 Apr 2025 09:08:36 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://stvpj.com/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /><item>
        <title>Why Product Managers Should Trust Their Gut When Data Falls Short</title>
        <link>https://stvpj.com/p/why-product-managers-should-trust-their-gut-when-data-falls-short/</link>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 Apr 2025 09:08:36 +0100</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://stvpj.com/p/why-product-managers-should-trust-their-gut-when-data-falls-short/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="https://stvpj.com/p/why-product-managers-should-trust-their-gut-when-data-falls-short/header.png" alt="Featured image of post Why Product Managers Should Trust Their Gut When Data Falls Short" /&gt;&lt;h1 id=&#34;why-product-managers-should-trust-their-gut-when-data-falls-short&#34;&gt;Why Product Managers Should Trust Their Gut When Data Falls Short
&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;As Product Managers, we’re often told to “let the data speak” and to rely on hard evidence to validate our hypotheses. And rightly so—data is a powerful tool for minimizing risk and understanding user behavior. However, there’s a vital piece of the product innovation puzzle that is often overlooked: intuition. When the right data isn’t available or doesn’t exist, your gut can be your most valuable ally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, some of the most transformative innovations we celebrate today were born in moments when data was either nonexistent or irrelevant. Let’s explore why Product Managers shouldn’t shy away from trusting their instincts when navigating uncharted waters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;data-is-a-compass-not-a-crystal-ball&#34;&gt;Data Is a Compass, Not a Crystal Ball
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Marty Cagan, author of &lt;em&gt;Inspired&lt;/em&gt;, emphasizes the limitations of relying solely on data. He writes, &lt;em&gt;“Data is essential, but it only tells you about the past. If you want to invent the future, you have to look beyond the data.”&lt;/em&gt; Data can show us what has worked before, but it rarely points to what will work in the future, especially when you’re venturing into unexplored territory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a Product Manager tries to innovate in a space that’s new or undefined, historical data often falls short. Imagine being the first to propose something like the iPhone. What data would have validated that hypothesis? None. Yet, Steve Jobs famously said, &lt;em&gt;“People don’t know what they want until you show it to them.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;visionary-thinking-often-precedes-data&#34;&gt;Visionary Thinking Often Precedes Data
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some of the most game-changing innovations weren’t built on data—they were built on a deep understanding of human needs and the courage to make bold decisions. Steve Jobs’ intuition about user experience led to products that redefined industries. Had Apple waited for market research to prove demand, the iPhone might never have happened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, Pawel Huryn, product leader and author, argues that &lt;em&gt;“great product managers are great storytellers—they imagine a better world and then find a way to make it real.”&lt;/em&gt; In the early stages of product development, storytelling and vision often fill the gaps where data cannot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;when-to-trust-your-gut&#34;&gt;When to Trust Your Gut
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Trusting your gut doesn’t mean ignoring data—it means knowing when it isn’t enough. Here are some scenarios where intuition can be invaluable:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When entering uncharted markets:&lt;/strong&gt; No historical data exists for truly innovative ideas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When experimenting with new paradigms:&lt;/strong&gt; Early-stage products often lack the metrics to guide decisions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When responding to qualitative insights:&lt;/strong&gt; User interviews and anecdotal evidence sometimes reveal truths that numbers can’t.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pawel Huryn puts it succinctly: &lt;em&gt;“Your gut feeling is your subconscious mind processing years of experience, knowledge, and observations. It’s not irrational; it’s informed.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;balancing-data-and-intuition&#34;&gt;Balancing Data and Intuition
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The key is to strike a balance. Use data when it’s available and relevant, but don’t let the absence of perfect data paralyze you. Great Product Managers are not just analysts—they’re visionaries who can navigate ambiguity and take calculated risks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Marty Cagan reminds us, &lt;em&gt;“At the end of the day, your job is to solve problems in a way that creates value for your customers and your company. Don’t let data become an excuse for inaction.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        <item>
        <title>How Security and Data Governance Improve User Experience</title>
        <link>https://stvpj.com/p/how-security-and-data-governance-improve-user-experience/</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 19 Apr 2025 14:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
        
        <guid>https://stvpj.com/p/how-security-and-data-governance-improve-user-experience/</guid>
        <description>&lt;img src="https://stvpj.com/p/how-security-and-data-governance-improve-user-experience/header.png" alt="Featured image of post How Security and Data Governance Improve User Experience" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enhancing User Experience through Security and Data Governance: A Product Manager&amp;rsquo;s Perspective&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We live in an age where our personal information is increasingly digitised. Every click, every search, and every online purchase leaves behind a digital footprint. As a Product Manager, my main goal is not just to deliver feature-rich applications but to ensure that these applications are safe, trustworthy, and provide an excellent user experience. One might assume that optimising for security and data governance might hinder the user experience. Contrary to that belief, I&amp;rsquo;m here to argue that enhancing security and data governance is, in fact, a significant booster to the overall user experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Building Trust&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
The most apparent benefit of security optimisation is trust. When users realise that a product or service prioritises their security, they are more likely to trust it. Trust, in the digital realm, is not just a nice-to-have; it&amp;rsquo;s a necessity. A product that loses its users&amp;rsquo; trust might as well lose its users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Smooth Experience with Fewer Interruptions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Imagine a scenario where an application gets compromised. This would lead to downtimes, emergency maintenance, or even data breaches. Each of these outcomes disrupts the user experience. By investing in security from the get-go, we ensure a seamless experience for our users, free from unexpected disruptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Empowerment through Transparency&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Data governance isn&amp;rsquo;t just about keeping user data safe; it&amp;rsquo;s about being transparent about how this data is used. By giving users a clear insight into what data is collected, why it&amp;rsquo;s collected, and how it&amp;rsquo;s used, we empower them. An empowered user is an engaged user, and an engaged user is the key to enhanced user experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tailored User Experiences without the Creepiness&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
One of the main reasons companies collect data is to provide a more tailored experience to their users. However, there&amp;rsquo;s a fine line between personalisation and intrusiveness. Proper data governance ensures that personalisation is done right, without crossing the boundaries of user comfort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compliance Equals Access&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
In today&amp;rsquo;s global market, regulatory compliance is not optional. Regulations like GDPR in Europe or CCPA in California have strict requirements regarding data privacy and security. By adhering to these regulations, we not only avoid hefty fines but ensure that our product is accessible to a broader audience without regional restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Future-proofing the Business&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Security threats and data misuse are not static; they evolve. By building a foundation based on robust security and data governance, we are preparing our product for the challenges of the future. This ensures that our users continue to have a consistent and safe experience even as digital landscapes change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;User Feedback and Continuous Improvement&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
When users feel safe and trust a platform, they are more likely to provide genuine feedback. This feedback is invaluable. It allows us to continuously refine and improve, ensuring the user experience keeps getting better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, security and data governance are not mere checkboxes in the product development process. They are crucial pillars that hold the weight of user trust and engagement. By integrating them into the core of our products, we are not sacrificing user experience; we are elevating it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember, in the end, it&amp;rsquo;s not just about building a product; it&amp;rsquo;s about building a relationship with our users. And like any successful relationship, it must be built on trust, transparency, and mutual respect.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
